[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
boom all right everyone welcome
to the stowawa i am peter lindbergh the
steward of the stoa
and the stowa is a place where we cohere
in dialogue about what matters most at
the nice
edge of this very moment and uh
today we got uh my buddy eric brown
one of the fine people at high existence
and he brought today with them
jamie combs the creator of four game
model
or four game dynamics and he goes by the
name of
captain simple on
twitter and this model uh
i quite like it and it's uh quite
elegant
and um and we're gonna we're gonna
explore today
and for those of you who who are
regulars of the stoa uh we talk about or
at least i talk about something called
the metagame we used to have this
metagame mastermind here
and uh i remember i was doing this
presentation for daniel kazanjian's
medimine mastermind
group and i just came up with the term
uh definition on the spot for for
not on the spot but beforehand uh for
the metagame and i defined it as playing
the metagame helps us discover
the right relationship with the ecology
of games we are currently playing
so the idea there there's like an
ecology of games and you can kind of
zoom out
see it and decide which one to play and
i find it quite compatible with this
four
game model because um jamie and jimmy
will talk about there's like four
ontological game categories uh the short
game the mid game the long game the deep
game
uh and um they all have kind of you know
a different uh
way to go about playing them well so
that being said uh it's going to be
standard still a format
jamie and eric are going to like uh chat
about it i imagine they might pull me
into that conversation too
and then we'll do the q a so if you have
any questions
um just throw in the chat i'll
call you i'll meet yourself if you don't
want to be on youtube indicate that
so that being said i will allow
eric and jamie to mute themselves and
i'll
tag whoever wants to be taped in
okay we on great thank you peter
hello everybody eric
um yeah today since we're short on time
i think this is going to be so much fun
um what we're going to do is we're going
to produce uh talk about this funny
little conceptual model for game
dynamics which today we're just going to
present as
kind of a lens and kind of a game so we
can pick up on the metagame frame easily
enough
and you guys probably already have lots
of lenses to look at what's going on so
this is just another one
the nature of what i want to do today is
kind of explain it as quickly as
possible because it's nice and simple
and then i'll put it on and kind of look
at the nature of what's going on and
look at people
look at this kind of accelerating
complexity that's got everybody a little
jumpy
um and seeing if this lens is helpful
for that
does that make sense um
again so if you take it in from the idea
of again it's just a lens right
and we all start from this common
question of what the is going on
and what should i do and how should i do
it and where to begin
and i think that there's this common
sense of
overwhelm and four game takes that and
says okay let's start
in any number of places but let's start
by saying that is the metagame
and it's a metagame that's characterized
by four games happening simultaneously
and the nature of what we're trying to
do is not to win them
but to balance them juggle them get into
flow with them
now that's just a conceit that we have
by putting on the lens and playing the
game
so we're not trying to make a
philosophical statement about that what
it is
but if we're going to address this kind
of accelerating complexity coming at us
as a mystery boom what metaphor are we
going to put on that in such a way that
we can interact with that
um in a pleasant way in a productive way
so that's what four game
is about and the first kind of idea is
well part of the nature of the problem
is just too much is too much
and there's just too much coming at you
and of course you're going to be
paralyzed in the same way of trying to
juggle 15 balls
there's an infinite amount of balls so
the game can't be who can juggle more
balls
um so four games looked at these four
different games that are happening
simultaneously
and give them names for them that you're
already probably a little familiar with
first one is that everyone knows is
their long game
your long game this is your narrative
the narrative part of your life
you tell it in story form it's more than
just your plan of what you're gonna do
it's more like your life script and you
have it with you right now and i could
sit and we could talk to any one of you
and we could pull it out of you
people like peter who have put it online
we all kind of know a little bit
about what his long game is right and
we're here because of his long game
you know we're enjoying the mid game
it's the fruit of his long game
but so this long game is this narrative
realm that we have and there's all sorts
of models within this narrative realm
that are fantastic there's all sorts of
tips and tools that are fantastic
there's all sorts of giants in the field
and there's a whole lineage
looking back at wowie look at the power
of long game and what we can do with it
but you can't put long game in your hand
you can't bump your head on it
it's an intangible narrative thing but
if we just say phenomenologically in the
present
not trying to make any statement about
existence we could all tell our long
game and it would be very revealing
so that's a long game everybody's a
little bit familiar with that
um inside that long game if you start to
break it up of course you could
granule get it as granular as you like
but the 80 20 of the big chunks within
your long game if i was going to break
your long game down
i'm going to want to break it down like
a story what's your role what's your
goal what's your path
there's obstacles along the way
characters and villains
that whole idiom applies in the world of
long game
so that's part of what's going on right
now but if we say what's part of going
on right now
with you there's more than that than
just the story of what's going on
you also have say your short game you
have your inner world going on your
your body's going on your toenails are
going on thoughts are going on emotions
are going on all simultaneously
that's your short game also a well-known
and lots of different models
talk about short game martial artists
yoga yogis
all sorts of people are familiar with
short games stoics
so managing your short game and again in
the world of short game
you can break it up into saying it's the
swirling mix of mental stuff
emotional stuff and physical stuff
simultaneously happening everywhere all
over at once
wowie um so short game again all sorts
of
techniques and people and lineages and
tips and tricks
of managing that game except you can't
get out of any of these games but you
can play them
differently so a whole different little
set of labels for that
but there's more to you than that too so
yeah you've got the story about what's
going on and you've got your physical
sensation and your mental thoughts and
your emotional feelings
but you also have the chair you're
sitting in and the computer we're on and
the system we're enjoying together
in the air you're breathing and you've
got a whole mid-game situation around
you
again which you can get as granular as
you like but mid game you can bump your
head into
that's your environment that's your
systems that's your actual gadgets
and those work together with your short
game and your long game
again this isn't anything new this is
just kind of a
a cleaner way of labeling what you
already know to be true
which makes it less teaching but more
showing
and then playing and then the last game
is your deep game which is uh more of a
metaphorical game
and this is an interesting one because
the deep game goes all the way to the
edge of where we would all go if we had
hours to talk this out
which is mystery we'd end up overlooking
at this void of mystery and
with a cosmic shrug of i don't know what
it is
and if i did i couldn't put it into
words but when we communicate it we back
down there to some kind of metaphorical
sense of what's going on
and i call that your deep game i don't
know what's going on but it's like a
river i don't know what it's going on
but it's like a
parade i don't and it can be on a macro
in terms of your ground of being
or it could be a micro in terms of a
project the stowa is a digital campfire
that metaphor frames this um so within
that
deep so when you're staring at mystery
in a four game lens
you recognize the name of the game is
mystery there's no escaping that that's
where all the fun is
the next layer so that's the meta meta
game if you want the meta meta games
mystery
the metagame next is what metaphor are
you going to put around that mystery
that gives you a sense of identity and
purpose and connection and resonance
that matches everything else and then
the nature of playing those four games
well
is getting those into alignment or flow
of some kind
and you may or may not have ever heard
those terms but you'll probably have
been in that state
where your short game your mid game your
long game and your deep game are all
click it
and aligned and you get this emergent
feeling of man i am on
point and it feels like peter you've had
that i feel like i've been watching
peter do that
for the last couple of months with his
podcast and still and all of this
and he's been nice enough to document it
um but that
that kind of feeling where hey my deep
game in terms of how i conceive of
what's going on
matches my long game authentically of
the role i want to play in the world and
what i want to think is important and
what i'm not willing to do
and i've got gadgets and environment a
mid game and a community around me and
if i don't have it i'm going to build it
and that's how i'm going to focus my
time and my energy and my
put my thoughts and when all of those
get tied up whether it's an individual a
culture or an organization
whatever you want to call it wow
suddenly complicated nuanced things can
get done
swiftly by a diverse group of people and
that seems to me to be the nature of
what who gives a why is it
important well i think it's why is this
important because a lot of people
are facing accelerating complexity and
the nature of what they don't have
is a vocabulary of all vocabularies or a
meta gadget
to sim to not reduce it but to refine it
so you can access more
swiftly and so what i think you guys
will find when you put the lens on and
start looking at stuff
is you know more than you in four game
dynamics you know more than you think
you knew
because you recognize oh yeah check out
the long game on elon musk
oh yeah check out the deep game on this
guy or that guy
and suddenly you can learn a lot quicker
because you're distilling into a common
language
and it i find it connects people and for
instance we're already this whole group
you've got is already
connected by some kind of common long
game i mean certainly by the digital
campfire mid game thank you very much
peter but also by this
broader long game that you're starting
to set out which is f
which is what everyone's trying to put
their finger on and having listened to
you it seems like
we could have some fun exploring well
maybe the nature of the long game is
stealing the culture like oh okay that's
a narrative long game you could start to
build with
maybe it's not maybe it's some other
thing but the the next step it seems to
me when you have this whole pack of
uh well-intentioned hole thinkers
is they need a common vocabulary so they
can go from kind of a
tower of babylon situation to a little
bit
coherent in action where everybody's
getting in their own four-game
generative flow
i'm not trying to take your four games
and put them in mine i'm trying to get
you
so yours are in harmony with who you are
and what you want to do and how you
conceive it
and that's a very kind of personal
idiosyncratic thing
so it's more of a thing of giving the
content and then letting people play as
play as they wish that make sense
yeah totally um
i i can't go yeah okay yeah like uh
you guys are are having some uh
presentation portion or do you want me
to jump in with questions
um how would you like this to well i'll
tag off to eric or you but i'll
shut up for a while if that made sense
all right i think there's
i think there's one level uh worth
exploring here
jamie that was awesome thank you again
good to see everyone at the store this
place is beautiful
um i have a few a few comments to build
on what jamie said
um one of the things i've heard guy sing
stock and kind of
the circling crew talk about a lot is a
way of being you just have this essence
to you
one of the best examples probably
someone like alan watts terence mckenna
people with this character persona
personality to them
and one of the things that i love about
four game and when i first kind of
started talking to jamie about this was
your way of being is the sum total
of your four games right the way you act
the things you use
the you're trying to do in the
world like that
and what it allows for is like well you
can actually tweak all these dials
if you want to be a different way if you
want to be a different person tweak some
of the dials that you're doing
right tweak the metaphor that you're
following um
i think when people get into like the
spiritual world a lot their deep game
narrative actually changes fundamentally
and you can also see how it shifts down
and shifts up
if you change the metaphor of how you
view reality
your short game your feelings your
thoughts will change as a result it
cascades down but it also cascades up
you know you can see clean your room
with jordan peterson right
right in the mid game right if you
actually wanted to
change any of them you can start
anywhere that's a line that jamie has
that's
freaking awesome as well right pick a
game start anywhere if you want to make
a change you can actually just focus on
these i think another thing that's
worth addressing here is if any of these
are misaligned
like if your work doesn't actually match
up with
what you state your role is or what you
state like the metaphor is
you'll feel that friction and it comes
in like anxiety depression confusion
and so there is just a sense of yeah if
you can get everything in line
make it all cohesive and coherent you'll
actually thrive
a lot more from it and again just the
aesthetic
simple package that jamie has here is
what extremely what appealed to me just
extremely about this whole thing and
what jamie and i really clicked on in
one of our first conversations was oh
this isn't just an individual thing
like you can take this and you can put
it for schools of thought
like what's the four game of zen right
what's the four game of christianity
what's the four game of yoga what's the
four game of kovid
right jamie and i were talking about
that a little bit right it messed up
everyone's mid game started trickling
down into their short game
probably changed what you thought you
could do with your long game maybe if
you thought it was like the wrath of god
was affecting the deep game
but so you can do events you can do
people you can do everything just
through this lens
and you know this this group is
beautiful
of hosting a lot of different ideas a
lot of different people
a lot of different concepts and
sometimes
we can get into a mess of talking past
each other
i'm reminiscing on the sam harris jordan
peterson what is truth thing
where they were all actually trying to
talk about the same thing but talking at
different levels of it and it just
became this
this show basically if you can
actually have this shared language where
it's like okay
mid game level what's going on here deep
game level what's going on here
even people with highly polarized or
highly opposite or highly opposing views
can actually come together
for some semblance of a sane reasonable
conversation
and i think the i think the last point
on this is you know this zooms up from
individual to a company to a community
but to a
culture as well you know you look at
east versus west we talked about how
things trickle down
well if you have a story that you're a
kind of ghost in the shell
you know pulled here from the heavens
you know put here to kind of
suffer nature well that affects how
everything in your life would show up
but if you take you know there's a this
kind of eastern culture like we're
emerging from nature we're part of it
you see that reflect down into culture
into even the way they write
right their language is highly picture
based right it's more metaphorical it's
not as literal as the kind of western
uh anglicized alphabet
like there's just a huge
um ramification
long long tail effect to just how you
set up these games how cultures set up
these games how companies set them up
and there's a there's always been a
sense of how do we get like break
breakthrough velocity with the stuff
that's going on here because it's so
absolutely critical it's so absolutely
essential but so many of us are either
trapped in smaller communities have
trouble getting it out have trouble
making people care
and jamie's package of just this
relentlessly
simple relentlessly concise package
that's
actually highly aesthetic the whole
thing can be boiled down to those two
pictures that i shared earlier like
this is the stuff that can actually
virally spread and that's that's again
what appeals to me so much about this
model is it
encapsulates almost everything
we lost your audio there for a moment
there oh
uh i think all i was saying was you know
one of the advantages i think to this
is that the whole thing can actually be
summed up in those two pictures that we
were looking at
right just the the the four game
breakdown and how they're all nested
within each other
and if you can just ship that off to
people be like here
start here let's do this you actually
just bring together
everyone and get that kind of critical
mass the viral outbreak
of that's extremely useful to
people
so i think i think that's my little
mellow riff on all that
cool this was my internet that was uh
popping in and out so
i started with that uh jamie do you want
to add anything or should we pivot to
the the q
a portion i think no we can we can pivot
to uh
you know matching up to with what you're
doing because now here we are looking at
culture wondering what
i think if you put the lenses on and
you're gonna say okay the metagame is
how do we play our four games well our
collective problem is
how do we get our four game
together before it's too late
i mean language it as you wish you know
but i think part of that pro part of
that question which we can all look at
then i can we all
share looking at it is um whatever it is
as eric says we're going to have to be
able to put it and articulate it in a
simple clear
enough direct enough way that we can
engage a lot of people
and so i think simplicity and aesthetics
are going to have to be part of it
um to get to the next piece and that's
why i think you're this whole group and
what you're doing peter is
that's the group of people who's
naturally going to come up with
something like that
and do it i think so yeah no i think
share it and get talking about
whatever's on everybody's mind and i
think we'll find if you take what's on
your mind and look through a four game
lens
you might find a good insider too
excellent um so i'll uh
i'll launch us off with a first question
if you have any questions
throw in the chat um so
yeah like what came to mind is that when
you're saying that this whole project
i'm kind of putting my games out there
if you will
especially with my journaling it's
almost like i'm like writing the code of
my
like long game kind of all the games
really or like writing the script to it
live
and i'm inviting other people into that
process like
like i'm like part of me are just like
why am i even doing this right now
because it's like
it's it's really vulnerable but it's
it's actually rich because i i'm like i
don't have to hide anything
um and what came up there is uh samuel
berger who who's uh
since maker residence here at the store
he has something called uh live players
versus dead players
and in essence a live player is a person
or institution that can
basically create something that hasn't
been created before and a dead player
can only be effective
uh following a script um
and so like and this is the whole thing
about authenticity which i think the
etymology of that is
to um be the author of one's own life uh
so you're like authoring your kind of
your own script
so do you have any thoughts about that
about this sort of like self-authoring
process with each games and i find it
really useful too kind of like honing in
on okay this is a mid game that i gotta
write i'm following a like a dead script
here or following a dead script a long
grain
etc uh yeah i would say um
all the the life scripting stuff that's
a great in four game speech that's a
real long gaming skill
absolutely that so and that's turning
what's going on
into a story that kind of pulls you
towards it and feels authentic
so i would say that that's now you can
tell a story about
the changes in your mid game or you can
tell a story about the evolution of your
four games like if we were going to
interview you peter
we'd i'd want to talk to you about the
evolution of your four game
well you didn't always have this mid
game you didn't always have this level
you know and put it together um but so
you could when i think of life for um
authoring
i always kind of put four games four
game authoring author not your life the
role you want to be the mid game you'd
like to have the activities you like to
do the feelings you'd like to feel
you won't hit it of course but that
specificity
um help helps give give pull and the
more aligned it is and the more you can
see it
you know that's when everybody's talking
vision and oh my god i got drawn to it
those are four games that are really
personally aligned
and so self-authoring for me is a great
long game
so you know jordan peters says
self-authoring good long game advice
clean your room
good mid-game advice a good example of
starting anywhere
yeah i have one uh i've won one comment
to add on that
which is uh you know it's nice it's nice
to have an idea that the work you're
doing is actually effective
or that it's actually going to work and
you're not just kind of spraying and
praying a bunch of random
everywhere
and again you know i spoke if if any one
of these things is lacking you're
actually going to feel it
in whatever way that is if it's short
mid it's probably just a physical like
discomfort anxiety thing
but if it's on the upper levels like
you're talking existential dread
like complete nihilism stuff like that
so if you can actually
you can almost use it to diagnose where
you're at
right if you feel like life is
completely pointless
and yet you're filling it with the short
mid game stuff cars money
you know fancy stuff uh it's never going
to fix it because you're not addressing
it in the right
realm you actually have to get your
story and why you're here in check
which has absolutely nothing to do with
the material world right because it's
intangible
right it actually gets less tangible as
you go up and so it's like look
if you actually do want to self author a
figure out what you're actually lacking
in
and then that actually gives you a sense
of what you can do
to fix those things and address them and
bring them into line
because they're a whole bunch of people
you know running the hamster wheel of
like well let me just
get the the smart watch optimize myself
and that'll
suddenly fix the grand narrative of why
i'm here
it's like no man that's not how that
works so actually it can be used to kind
of hone your
your focus and what you're actually
working on because yeah you know if you
break them all down where am i now
where do i want to be how do i want to
feel
you know then you have a then you have
that path and it's just a matter of
showing up and doing it
rather than always feeling like i don't
know what i need to do next
it actually gives you some like answers
to that some steps
uh like in an inverse of that too um
tim ferriss came to mind like you know
the knowing the right game domain
uh like i think he said something once
where it's like let's say if you
um are feeling bad maybe because you
didn't have a good night's sleep or
something
and then you're trying to like you know
have an existential crisis and try to
solve the
life's mysteries meanwhile you just need
to eat right or go to bed at a certain
time
and focus on that kind of nickname or
short game
yeah i would say ferris is is a good
example of a whole thinker
he'll point out a problem that presents
over here but maybe there's a solution
over
over here um but also a good example of
since he's not there's not a common word
for it we don't quite know
when he's jumping to a deep game thing
to a short game thing to a mid game
thing
so it helps i think regular people kind
of digest
these four game proficient people
i can understand what they're saying i
can understand jordan peterson i can
understand elon musk i may not
be able to juggle 50 balls but i can
distill it into the fourth
80 20 what he's talking about which i
found allows you to learn a lot quicker
from a lot more people
well actually there's a the ferris
example
is actually fantastic because it shows
the evolution of the games
over time because if you if you're
following like right now what he's been
going through in the past few years like
he's doing the the psychedelic medicine
push but actually like this week you
know he released a big thing about
childhood trauma
you know addressing like deep inner
emotional wounds and so he progressed
from
again trying to fill like the trauma
higher level stuff with the success fame
money stuff
didn't work at all started doing some
kind of narrative inner emotional work
got more results and is actually like
again he's aligning it and seeing
a lot of results from it so i think he's
a fantastic example of
yeah you just gotta put your effort in
the right places and it'll actually come
through for you
yeah and a good example of starting
anywhere and getting everywhere
yeah yeah very cool
um rain you had a few questions if you
can choose one
yeah thanks thanks for being here eric
and jamie
um i had a question about
this you mentioned a couple times the
benefit of a shared
language a shared framework um
which um seems you know true
a priori that that we need to have this
mutual understanding in mutual terms
um in terms of the culture cultural and
intellectual landscape
finding our way how i see it out of this
post-modern morass
where we can actually make sense of
things again and and say that
some things are true or at least more
true than others
um is a big task without falling back
into modernist
paradigms um that say this is the
this is the one way to talk about things
so um to make it more personal
i'm sort of like unins uninspired
um so to speak from um
you know another model or another
framework so how do you
how would you propose to engage
meta-modern thinkers who
really don't care what the le the tools
what the
the words of the framework are as long
as it's
something that they can fluidly step
into
in order to make sense in that moment in
that context
yeah i would say that's just exactly
what it's for you have a long game
call it whatever you want you have a mid
game you have a short game
you don't like the language or the frame
or whatever but the nature of you
progressing from whatever state
of affairs you are now to a more complex
richer
one way or another one model or another
one yoga or another
it's going to be taking this
multi-dimensional whatever you call
situation you find yourself in
and being able to put it in your own
mind in such a way that you could
feel like you've got some agency on it
and take things from a mental realm and
put them into a mid-game realm
so it's really agnostic about forcing
the language down everyone who are
really fussy about it's a lens call it
what you want pick your own metaphor
this is just kind of getting started to
make the point of
whatever you want to call those
dimensions you can't not have them
and we can get more granular we could
make more dimensions we could forget all
the forms and have no dimensions at all
but there's some virtue if you get it to
just a few
you can have a high leverage without
being too overwhelmed
which i found has allowed you to get
complex things done over time
with a lot of people who do have
different models like i don't have to
agree on a lot of things if we have the
same long-term goal
right if we have the same short game
attitude what's going on in your mind
and mind is different we'll get along
just fine
so it allows you to to not have to do
that
and get those bases covered any which
way that works with people
one of my early jobs as a kid is i was a
trainer
and people want to come and they want to
talk about something instead of doing it
and it helps fix that it's like instead
of getting hung up on the lingo
it's direct pointing is a little bit of
the spirit
so i find the meta modern people are the
most interesting
because they've gone and all they
recognize that it's multi-dimensional
they've done a lot of research down a
lot of different dimensions so
they've got a lot of models and they can
connect a lot of things
what they find when they look through
four games is they start to put things
together
they're like oh i noticed the
similarities between the long games of
all this huxley and alan watts or the
mid game between
king arthur and alexander or whatever so
i think you guys have a lot of fuel for
the
fire if that makes sense so i'm really
sensitive to no it's absolutely not a
dogma
it's a it's a way of looking and we can
all put it on and look at it
and and react to it differently but if
the nature of someone's life or a
company or a culture is they're stuck
when you put on the lens you'll find one
of their four games is jacked up their
long game doesn't make sense their mid
game is counterproductive
their behaviors are self-destructive or
their their framing
is self-defeating and no amount of
fixing one without awareness of the
other is going to get them out of the
problem you know no amount of cleaning
your room will work if you never get
around to authoring your life is that
does that answer your question yeah
that's helpful thank you
yeah i actually don't have more to to
say directly on that but
one of the things that i also love about
this is like
this is where we're at with this like
i'm looking in the chat like these are
freaking amazing questions
and for me it's actually just a sense of
i would love to know what your answer is
right you you guys have the the graphics
you you know you have the language now
it's just like yo we're
we're doing this on the fly like we're
building this as we go right we jumped
off the cliff and we're building the
airplane
there's definitely a feeling in me where
it's like yeah this has
this has wings right this thing can run
it can definitely fly and it's been
useful in my own thinking my own life my
own conversations but
we're definitely not here like we have
all the answers like there's uh and
that's part of why we actually were
excited to come to the stowe and stuff
introduce it to some smart ass people
because it's like look
yo this resonates like let's build this
together like let's answer some of these
questions because they're freaking
really good questions
very cool uh there's a question on
relationships
which is at the edge of my thinking i
was actually writing a journal about
this
um so michael if you would mute yourself
and ask your question
yeah yes i was thinking like how does it
fit in
into people in your life like close
close family
spouses children friends and also in
your
in your second circle of community and
and
people at work and also in the wider
circle if you look to a town or a nation
or or globally so
because it's not this not not in the
silo so what do you are you thinking
about that
yeah i find a lot of of the relation bit
of the family comes into that long game
role
piece like what roles are you know i
distinguish role from identity
right your role as a father your role is
a business a role as a teacher a role as
a steward
those are the roles you kind of commit
to from a long game point of view
so in terms of social interaction a lot
of what's going on
is we're trying to play our roles well
um and so a lot of that in terms of
relationship
until you get to really close personal
is we're relating role to role
because i don't know all the intimate
pieces about you you know in business
and this group i think starts to have
some identity
because not only do we share a goal some
version of a
of a cleaner greener future everybody's
trying to figure out what their roles
are
in that longer plan and that's why i
think a lot of community you have to
have a long game
because before we know our roles and how
we're going to relate what are we trying
to do
and how are we trying to do it what do
we think is going on and what what are
we going to use to get there
so i think i find that a lot of the
social relations
once there's trying to be a purpose or
something to be done um the long game
roles
start to bring out the requirements of
the relationship
if that makes sense
yeah i like that any follow-up michael
yeah i'm thinking like when suddenly
there if there's a
conflict between the roles uh some
your children want this but you have to
work
do an extra project at work at the same
time
a family family member wants this of you
so how do you handle like the
the divergence of dissociation yeah
that's a good
that's a great case that's a
multi-dimensional problem
yeah right i mean you've got your career
to worry about you're all anxious and
maybe you
you know that's a perfect example and
that's where the agency is
if you say hey you've got a real four
game problem in that situation what are
you going to do about it
you're going to do a mid-game remedy
you're going to do a short game remedy
you're gonna fit you so it gives you
options i think to take a situation like
that
that without any kind of framework your
emotions are gonna be the presenting
problem
and then you're not gonna be able to
have a clear way of what to do how to do
it
that's gonna roll off happen immediately
and maybe that's your long game maybe
you want to live life like that you know
leaf in a mountain stream
that's one way to do it but it's still a
long game
if that makes sense yeah thanks
i got a follow-up uh statement slash
question
um in the pickup artist community they
have something called game
and um i i may have may or not have been
involved in that community in the past
now i'll
leave that a mystery but i dabbled in
some of the literature let's put it that
way
and uh yeah they call something game
having good game
and basically you're good with women you
can kind of you know
pick up someone you're attracted to uh
and you can kind of like to use martin
buber's um
i it relating versus i vow relating like
i it relating you're instrumentalizing
someone
to get something uh um and then you can
have like i
games with kind of pickup artist or
sales or negotiation or whatever
and then i i i thou relating is sort of
um connecting with someone on a deeper
level like recognizing the the god
within each other
uh and a lot of these intersubjective
practices that we practice here at the
stoa
kind of gesture towards i thou way of
relating so how do
like if you want to say if those are two
different types of games that i it
constellation of games in the i thou
constellation of games how would that
fit in this
four game model you know um
yeah interesting you could do well if
you think i
it versus you know if you go to deep
game then you can say lots of ways we're
going to look at dp game there's going
to be
i and it self and other and i'm going to
alien i'm going to have some kind of
dualistic deep game that sets you up and
really as opposed to a holistic deep
gain
it says hey me and the other and my
metaphor we're really the same thing
so those i see those as kind of riding
on two different
deep games of what's what's going on and
when you recognize that hey we're kind
of the same thing i'm not here to
exploit you
you've got four games i'm here to
empower you and light you up so you can
go do
what you want to do i'm not trying to
put ideas in your head i'm trying to
give you a language so you can go write
your own poetry
that that that difference um and that's
where i think
in the deep game the more holistic point
of view
it is and it doesn't matter necessarily
the form but just the spirit
of gestalt the back goes with the front
the front goes all of a piece it can be
mysterious
but it's not alienating to each other um
i think that drills down to a short game
attitude
that you have with other people which is
like hey hooray i
won't get your four games stronger what
else what else what's more satisfying
than that as opposed to
what you're saying that instrumentalized
where i've got some alienating deep game
that makes me go through life
trying to get people you know to execute
steps for me and so that's where you
might have a deep game problem but
wouldn't even know it but it would
present and you're this very exploitive
person
so a lot of people when they change or
they have a psychedelic experience or
some reason up in their deep game they
get that little holistic blip
and they realize the left hand isn't out
to get the right hand they're of a piece
then i think that kind of instrumental
way of looking at things
goes away you become less looking at the
world like a gold mine and more looking
like the world like a garden
and therefore your role changes in what
you're trying to do
so if that makes sense would that be
like the flip between the finite game
versus infinite game and use carson's
language
yes pro yes yeah you could have finite
games within the infinite game but you
take them sincerely not too seriously
and that's why the whole game metaphor
again if the framing of the
one of the virtues of the game is a
metaphor whoever uses it
is by the time it drills down to your
short game it helps you have confidence
and a playful feeling
which is what you need to get into flow
so if i have divine judgment as my deep
game it's hard to get playful divine
flow vibe
going in my short game so that's why a
lot of these things where you're trying
to elicit
confidence they want to try to make it
some type of game
because that's we can engage with games
again with sincerity without too much
seriousness
and that's what it gives it pull
and you want to do it for its own right
and as long as it's a generative game
and that's what if the four game
elements are just right it's a
generative game
you're playing a generative game peter
you've the stow is a generative piece of
mid-game
the more you do it the better you get
because you've got your things aligned
that's the kind of thing we're after
whereas if your law if your deep game
was some kind of alienating thing and so
all this was a
exploitive money grab that would be a
different four games that you don't have
that wouldn't be generative
from my point of view does that make
sense
yeah i got a little i got a little
comment on that as well
which actually ties into i think this is
going to tie into michael's earlier
question as well which is
there's been some semblance of this
conversation where we're actually coming
to this
uh with answers already like oh let me
look at zen through this and actually
just inject into it
i think it can also be really useful to
start pulling things out and actually
getting the initial questions
rather than the answers for them like uh
with with michael's thing about family
and like choosing between family and
money
if i actually look at my life through
this and what and where the tension is
arising
a question comes up where it's like am i
actually okay
putting my work before my family and
that could spawn
very very beneficial things for you and
i think to peter's question as well it's
like
are we actually okay with some of the
smartest
people our countries produce earning the
most amount of money to contribute to a
global
socioeconomic system that treats the
world as i it
like is that actually are we comfortable
continuing that
and that question can come from the lens
but it's actually a starting point it's
not the
it's not the end insertion it's actually
okay now i'm seeing where the friction
is coming from
why my stomach feels weird when the
smartest ass people are trying to
sell me stuff on facebook and it's like
where do i go with that
what does realigning that look like and
so yeah i think this actually ties into
jamie's point it can be generative
in that way of actually adding more or
giving us places to start
rather than just coming from this as a
kind of post-hoc analysis
so the long game of stealing the culture
is back at the store officially after
after hearing that
i stopped using that phrase but i'm just
back um
do you have anything to add to that
jamie before i go to the next question
nope that was good okay um
alex you had a question
[Music]
thank you peter so um i'm trying to see
if i can phrase this question
the very language of game is something
that you
do with others in society so it has a
lot to do with external validation
it says my connection is unstable so i
hope i'm not too choppy here
so it seems to me it's a very individual
lens
to look at society and who you are and
how you
interface with society it's kind of like
what neo and morpheus do
when they plug into the matrix you know
they're in the matrix and they're
playing a game
and then they come out of the matrix
presumably when you come out of the
matrix
you're that metaphysical self self your
that true identity and you even have it
here who is that true self who is that
real
you who is that metaphysical
consciousness that's aware
um that you have a body on earth and
presumably
there there's no game that's your true
identity
so for me it's it's contradictory to say
that there's a metaphysical game
because that's external validation like
you know i'll get laid by saying i'm
like some great guru
right and i'm getting this external
validation because i have this deep game
right but that's not why one should have
a deep game
one should have a deep game not for any
external validation but because that's
your true self
so i'm i'm finding a contradiction in
terms there
sure yeah let me help it that the real
thing we're saying is mystery the only
thing we're asserting the whole game is
played on mystery which isn't
which isn't even asserting anything
about a true self i don't know
but the truest thing i know i don't know
it's a cosmic shrug
now if i want to handle it i can put any
kind of frame on it i want if i don't
want to put game i could put dance i
could put melody i could put garden
we're already it's already a conceit to
put the frame on it so i'm not mistaking
the metaphor
but to get a sense of identity you're
going to have a relationship
to the metaphor because you can't put
language on
mystery so if it's a way if if it's kind
of like an ocean
well then my identity is maybe kind of
like a wave on the ocean
now that's not to say that is what it is
it's just what it's kind of like
and that's where my short game is going
to resonate oh if that's what i really
think if i really look in the face of
mystery and i say
god i don't know but it's kind of like
an ocean
well then that's deep game metaphor is
the one i'm operating with
and my identity is going to drill down
is that going to be the final truth
no you couldn't be in words anyway so
it's not trying to make that
i'm aware of that mistake you're talking
it's not trying to assert that
that's why starting at mystery i think
is the most honest place
then we can say great let's play with
language and see what we can come up
with as we all stare at this mystery
that makes sense but that's a good
question are specifically
trying to avoid that conflict
it's it's a great uh thank you um i find
it so interesting because yesterday we
had the session on
nihilism nihilism i don't even know how
to say the word
and this seems to be the opposite this
is the anti-nihilism
there's actually meaning in what we do
well because
yeah well because with wonder it in
mystery and i don't use unknowing or
anything i use mystery
because the flip side of mystery is
curiosity and wonder and that's just
what's going on and that
that you can self-validate even if you
don't know anything
you can say man that's true and that
everybody has regardless of their
culture or whatever they frame they put
on it
and if i find if we can start in good
faith there
that saves a lot of trouble downstream
i think there's i think there's one
other thing which is almost getting
to semantics but uh i i agree with how
you were describing the game
at some level but the other the other
way i would look at game is like
or at least play because you play games
of you know something you do for its own
sake
right it's d it's done because it is
just beautiful in and of itself you
actually don't do it you don't give it
damn about anyone else i'm doing this
because it gives me deep satisfaction
deep meaning deep
purpose whatever it is and there is a
i think there is a deep game lens where
it's like
what is going on here if it's not
playful
like if it wasn't going to be playful i
wouldn't do this this seems like a lot
of work for whatever the heck is
orchestrating this like
if i wasn't doing this for fun or
because the thing in itself was
beautiful
it probably just wouldn't be done and so
in that yeah
i think that's a another framing of at
least the game
the game semantics or the game wording
because it's like yo it's a
it's a thing in itself you don't
actually have to play any of these games
you could just sit and kind of do
nothing be an npc you know have
you know just go along but they are fun
games to play should you choose to
actually like
show up at the table and start playing
them yeah and the the
the frame of game forces you to think of
play
you know so we're going to be playing
here that's not like working
um exactly or culture war or cultural
war or something
some frame that's you can't get out of
it it's there's no scenario although
you're locked in from the metaphor and
it's going to be tribes fighting and
killing and that's
there's no plan in that and if you're
trying to get into generative flow which
requires a sense of kind of creative
wonder and play
and authenticity you've snipped it off
before you've ever
started and then you layer into that a
mid game that's not conducive and
all of that so these it's kind of
non-obvious
i don't know not obvious significance of
the of the deep game
and the play bit because it's a short
hop from play to creative
it's a short hop from it's a mysterious
universe so let's build this on creative
and we're trying to get you into
generative flow so you can be in
creative flow
you know playful creative that that
spirit where
yeah it's coming out of you nobody's
telling you it's just that emergent
thing in the
in the moment we're trying to spark
spark that
[Music]
and another thing uh came to mind with
the framing and this may be a question
to eric um
so like we need to worry at a previous
session she had uh
she said like the problem with a lot of
these sense making spaces is there's so
much epistemic
fat that was a term she used and i
teased her i'm like the term epistemic
fat is kind of epistemic
benefit you know like people in the
space and then i'm sure eric we would
like geek out and like you know
masturbate about all these mental models
and these kind of these concepts
um but like from my dale carnegie
background i'm a dale carnegie trainer
it's the great thing about dale carnegie
he just simplified things and just spoke
in very common language
and to double click on rain's point
before um
it's kind of cool having kind of a slew
of mental models they all might be
pointing like the fingers at the moon
but picking one that really resonates
the audience you're gonna speak to
um so i'm curious if you have any
thoughts on that
yeah the so among among my friend groups
here i'm probably the one just most
personally interested in the whole
kind of sense making stove space and
the amount of times i've sent a daniel
schmuckenberger video to people and
it's never been watched is tragic it's
absolutely tragic because i'm a huge fan
of everything going on in this space and
i was like
this is critical like let's do this all
all hands on deck
and it is just falling like it is just
falling right at the face we never
never even get in the door and it's
tragic because at least at the end of
the at least at the end of the day
everyone in the world is going to have
to be playing some game you know this is
the classic game b
talk as well where it's like at some
point in time we're all going to have to
get on that ship
and there are a lot of people who have
no time energy
capacity to do some of this and so there
is this just
what is the most relentlessly
mercilessly
simple aesthetic approachable way that
people can actually get in the door
and not feel overwhelmed by the freaking
jordan hall daniel schmuckenberger back
and forth that they can't even
follow at all this at least feels like a
bridge
right the stepping stones of like here
you know let's talk in this way like
here's some language that you can use so
you can actually show up because i know
you want to
maybe you're just nervous maybe just you
know have
have a i don't know lower energetic
capacity right now but there is just
this sense of
the simple the aesthetic stuff that can
be mean
right like by definition like stuff that
can be memed and spread virally that is
actually what we need to
get the beautiful absolutely beautiful
brilliant ideas people are coming up
with here just to everyone else
because it's super easy and the stow is
fantastic it's super easy to feel like
everyone in the world is here
but like they're not they're really just
not go look at the trending youtube
videos of the day and like you'll be
surprised how far apart they are from
what's going on here
and so yeah is there anything that we
can offer people
that is just here's five minutes this is
super approachable i think you'll love
it too it might actually help
um i don't think we can underestimate
just how important that stuff is and
you know again it's what made me land
with jamie so strongly was like
this feels maybe if it's not the perfect
answer like a damn good step in the
right direction because this thing is
almost more aesthetic than it is
conceptual
and that was like something feels right
about that
you know it helps put it helps at least
me anyway come from a place of
appreciation
you can be like wow check out the long
game on daniel schmuckenberger wow
check out the mid game uh lindbergh's
megan well we check out the short game
on eric brown
and it has this ability of whatever you
want to call it we're all in the same
book and you can
you know what's the thing you know
bandits in the street recognize each
other immediately
yeah everybody that's trying to improve
things from a multi-dimensional
insight it seems like put a circle
around all of them
um they have a lot a lot more in common
and particularly once there's a little
bit of common lingo it doesn't it's not
a reduction bit
it's almost a refinement and a
connecting
um maybe gray you had a question
hi thank you guys i'm loving this
session it's really energetic i'm
feeling like it's really alive for all
of us um i'm
curious about like how tight are the
compartments
of these four different games does the
deep game have
like prominent influences on your short
game does your short game go all the way
to your deep game and vice versa
good question uh the answer i think is
loose and personal
and the cool thing about it is once you
get the lingo and the spirit of what
we're talking about
you could go check your own which you
will
which is what you really and that's
where it really gets interesting and
there's no right or wrong in it
there's just what it is and what you can
tweak and once you start
noticing but one of the things i think a
lot of people notice once they look at
it
is the relationship between their
emotional space which is where a lot of
problems show up
non-linguistic just
and if you don't have a thing to put it
it's like yeah that's where it presents
but part of that is because your long
game is jacked up
and no amount of you know pringles is
gonna fix it
if that makes sense um but the thing is
really looking inside of you and then
once you get a sense if you know your
own four games well then you don't have
anything to apologize
a sense of calm comes on because it's
not right or wrong
but you can at least step back and
articulate it
from your point of view and then nobody
can make you wrong
if that makes sense and you can be
really curious and admirable
about the parts that they have that are
different and then kind of meet on
common
bits without any kind of dominator
weirdness
going on yeah i actually have two uh
two images from jamie that i think are
fantastic ways to answer this i'm gonna
share my screen really quickly
so jamie continually comes back to this
kind of nested
image where your inner is nested in your
mid nested in your long nested in your
deep which i think is
absolutely correct and it kind of shows
the
proportion of influence like your deep
game your long game will
have a substantial impact
on what your short and mid actually end
up looking like you can
go the other way but i think it's i
think it's a lot harder
and then the other one i love is the
kind of taurus loop
um energetic donut where it actually
circles back in on itself right once you
once you wrap up a deep game it then
finds its way into well what does my
tuesday look like based on that
right if i suddenly believe that you
know i'm following the kind of yoga
hindu philosophy well
you know the way i spend my day is going
to look a lot different and then it
trickles back up up up and then you
actually see like okay
i'm a dedicated practicing yogi now and
that
reaffirms your relationship to your you
know your long narrative and your deep
game and it all just
circles back in on itself i think those
are
two really uh useful ways to to look at
how those things kind of play
play and dance with each other you know
it's fun in that sense of once you've
got the lens for it you can look at
someone's
four games from the outside but then you
can do the thought experiment
of getting inside their four games and
looking from the app from the inside out
and sometimes if there's somebody that
you really admire or feel connected to
try that what is it like looking through
their eyes feeling that thoughts all the
same time you can get a connection
um with other people and learn on
different levels
kind of non-linguistically uh so we're
almost at the hour would you guys have
like five minutes to stay afterwards or
do you have to leave right at the
tower yeah um so maybe we'll just do
one or two questions or statements uh
margaret
uh you had a cool question uh or cool
statement if you can unmute yourself
sure hi um so yeah this
whole conversation thank you jamie and
eric very much for sharing this is
really interesting
this whole conversation very strongly
reminds me of a game that
i know i played briefly in childhood and
come back to
periodically throughout my life which
other people might have also played
where
essentially the game was you could not
mention the game and as soon as you
mention the game you lose
and if you mention someone then you
cause them to lose as well
uh and this i mean it works with the
taurus model also of like an inverse
kind of
turning that inside out where instead of
the rule being like you don't mention
the game it's like no
we are all playing the game let's make
that explicit and then
move from there
yeah well that's great that's great i
hadn't heard of that that does sound
like a fun game
but yeah there's a there's a little bit
of that and there's a little bit of the
sense of
again once you hold the lens lightly and
you're not making a philosophical
statement you can't escape the games you
can't not
play the games you can't leave your mid
game you can't not you know
and then once you kind of accept that
there's kind of a
oh okay we're doing this vibe and then
it's a happening and a lot of anxiety it
seems to go away
but kind of in the spirit of what you're
talking about it's
not so much talking about swimming it's
actually swimming
you know
very cool and actually margaret and i
were in discussion of doing a series
of the short term series called the
communitas club where we're working on
the name
where we're going to look at different
social games like non-violent
communication
insight dialogue restorative circles
verbal keto and brings a practitioner in
to kind of
play with us so uh that's gonna be
really fun
um so yeah i think we should wrap it up
i'll i'll
let you guys uh jamie eric you have any
kind of closing thoughts for us this has
been a like a really awesome and
thought-provoking
actually no i'll share one thought
before i hand it over to you guys uh
like
my uh my pushback game the only concern
i have is
like this is one of those like models
that when you learn it it's like you
want to apply to everything right like
you're already making jokes
like when you first like oh as you're
playing short game right now playing
long game um
and the whole maslow's hammer or like
you know if you you have a hammer
everything becomes a nail
um so that's that's the thing that's
coming my line like well i'm not gonna
like over
overuse this over extend this model um
that being said any responses to that
and any final words from you guys
yeah no you're right that does what come
up the first thing about is it's
reductionist it's all you know there's
this
sense of like no no captain simple and
for me that's the first test there you
go there's a short game of motion see
what that
feels like start anywhere um and so it's
that kind of yeah
i don't know sneakily simple um
which i think is kind of part of its
charm but you're right that is the kind
of first thing and that's why
um in these early days we kind of put it
out there without too much explaining
to attract people like you and like
peter who recognize it without
being explained too much because you're
already
doing it well you're just not using the
lingo um
so but to close up i would just say that
you know in my telling of the tale if
the nature of what we're trying to do is
get our four games together before
it's too late
and the headline coming out of the stowa
is hey maybe we're going to steal the
culture
we're going to take all these whole
thinkers who can recognize the
multi-dimensionality of what's going on
but they've got different lingos but the
intention's good maybe the
next chance the stage of this long game
is some of us
start sharing a common lingo and moving
the ball a little bit on
sub projects in precisely the same way
peter's demonstrating with the stoa
on a smaller scale so it feels to me
like that's the nature of what
a positive long game looks out and it
can be dressed up in any number of ways
but what i think eric and i are doing
are kind of going around and just
direct pointing to people who are
already doing it well
and and i think that starts to be a
community of this is how the long game
starts to think different people like
you doing things like this
and i think the non-obvious move is
there has to be a playful
frame to it because warframes and
whatnot are just going to get you more
war yeah
yeah i guess i have two really quick
comments uh to address
and your thing peter every person here
has probably seen
that kind of multi-panel cartoon where
it's a bunch of dots and it's like this
is knowledge
and then there's some connecting lines
and it's like this experience and then
there's a whole
path and it's like this is wisdom
everyone knows or has a sense of what
the actual dots are they're like people
places things events whatever life
experience
what is the lines what are the lines
what's the connective
tissue that puts all that together
perhaps something like this it is
something that ties together all these
disparate things whether it's stuff in
your own life
whether it's different mimetic tribes
whether it's different levels of what
the is going on
uh and so actually like i say that
because
if done well this thing should actually
just disappear into the background
and serve just as connective scaffolding
and never actually be
need to be mentioned right but the
problem
is that as it stands right now there's
just a bunch of isolated islands
doing a whole bunch of wicked stuff with
no real way of talking to each other
or talking past each other or thinking
that they're actually doing different
things when they're doing the same
thing and so if there is if there can be
this little connective tissue
that puts everything together which
again jamie's
relentlessly simple like four lenses
with three things in each
might be a fantastic way to do that
and really my only closing comment is
one of the things i mentioned earlier
which is just like
yo we're building this like if you think
this is cool
answer some of the questions and send it
like i think this is relentlessly useful
i asked jamie to go on a conversation
with me and that's literally why i'm
here today
like this is very early days and if it
resonates if it lands like
you know come come build the future come
build that connective tissue that shared
language with us
because yeah it's a fun game to play
beautiful so i'll make some uh closing
announcements in a moment but
uh my friends thank you so much for
coming to stowa today that was a lot of
fun
a lot of gratitude being sent your way
uh and
in open invitation if you ever want a
workshop some kind of
session in the store that could maybe be
a ported to the wisdom gym about like
how to build a four game muscle um how
to kind of
play it let me know and i'm happy to
feel tested here at the stoa
um so a couple events uh tomorrow
we have uh agnes callard a famous
philosopher uh she's gonna have his
title
title the talk is can you know you're
wrong
and then she's basically asking the
question uh how do we know
uh when we're wrong so that should be
cool
that's at uh 8 p.m eastern time
um tyson i'm going to tell you and my
friend
uh you gotta you got some stuff to talk
about
sure thanks peter uh thanks eric and
jamie
for doing the session i enjoyed it quite
a lot and anytime that
uh playfulness is a big theme i
start to get excited to plug my event as
a space for people to come play
um with self-expression we practice
freestyle rap and spoken word
as an opportunity to deepen our
relationship with uncertainty
and develop our trust muscles in our
self
so that's every monday it's a really
open and approachable space so if anyone
wants to come check it out
it's mondays 8 30 eastern and i look
forward to seeing you there
yeah and that flowing with unknowingness
uh i'll drop the link in the moment uh
and there's another uh
game so that's the flowing with annoying
this tyson does is in our wisdom gym uh
we we have another game gonna be
entering the wizard gym the glass bead
game
lawrence lawrence curry clark uh he
previewed it uh this weekend and he's
going to come in every saturday i think
it's at 6 pm eastern time it's going to
start some i think in october
that's going to be dope it's going to be
weekly um
check out the events at the stowa.ca if
you like what we're doing here
whatever we're doing here if you want to
help us steal the culture and support it
you can support us on patreon
there's a link right there um yeah that
being said
eric jamie thanks again everyone thank
you for coming to the store today
thank you see you guys thanks jamie